My students and I work on very tiny robots.
أنا وتلامذتي نعمل على روبوتات صغيرة جدا.
Now, you can think of these as robotic versions
الآن تستطيع أن تعتبر هذه الروبوتات نماذج
of something that you're all very familiar with: an ant.
ﻷشياء مألوفة جدا: النملة.
We all know that ants and other insects at this size scale
وجميعنا يعلم بأن النمل والحشرات الأخرى بمثل هذا حجم
can do some pretty incredible things.
قادرة على عمل أشياء مذهلة.
We've all seen a group of ants, or some version of that,
جميعنا رآى مجموعة من النمل أو نموذجا من ذلك
carting off your potato chip at a picnic, for example.
تقوم بأخذ رقائق البطاطس خلال النزهة، على سبيل المثال.
But what are the real challenges of engineering these ants?
ولكن ما هي التحديات الحقيقية لهندسة هذا النمل؟
Well, first of all, how do we get the capabilities of an ant
حسنا، أولا وقبل كل شيء، كيف نحصل على قدرات النملة
in a robot at the same size scale?
في روبوت بمثل هذا الحجم؟
Well, first we need to figure out how to make them move
حسنا، أولا نحن بحاجة إلى معرفة كيفية جعلها تتحرك
when they're so small.
كونها صغيرة جدا.
We need mechanisms like legs and efficient motors
نحن بحاجة إلى آليات مثل السيقان والمحركات الفعالة
in order to support that locomotion,
من أجل دعم هذه الحركة.
and we need the sensors, power and control
ونحن بحاجة إلى المجسات والكهرباء وآليات التحكم
in order to pull everything together in a semi-intelligent ant robot.
من أجل ضم جميع المهام في روبوت "النمل الشبه الذكي".
And finally, to make these things really functional,
وأخيرا، لجعل هذه الأمور تعمل،
we want a lot of them working together in order to do bigger things.
نريد الكثير من هذه الروبوتات العمل معا من أجل عمل مهام أكبر.
So I'll start with mobility.
لذلك سأبدأ بمفاهيم الحركة.
Insects move around amazingly well.
الحشرات تتحرك وتتنقل بشكل مثير للدهشة.
This video is from UC Berkeley.
هذا الفيديو من جامعة بيركلي.
It shows a cockroach moving over incredibly rough terrain
ويظهر صرصورا يتحرك على أرض وعرة للغاية
without tipping over,
دون أن ينقلب،
and it's able to do this because its legs are a combination of rigid materials,
وهو قادر على القيام بذلك لأن سيقانه مكونه من مزيج مواد قاسية وصلبة،
which is what we traditionally use to make robots,
وهي ما نستخدمها عادة في صناعة الروبوتات،
and soft materials.
ومواد لينة أيضا.
Jumping is another really interesting way to get around when you're very small.
طريقة أخرى ومثيرة جدا للاهتمام للتنقل عندما يكون حجمك صغير جدا هي القفز.
So these insects store energy in a spring and release that really quickly
إن هذه الحشرات تخزن الطاقة على شكل زنبركي ومن ثم تفرج عن هذه الطاقة بسرعة فائقة
to get the high power they need to jump out of water, for example.
للحصول على الطاقة الكافية التي يحتاجونها للقفز من الماء، على سبيل المثال.
So one of the big contributions from my lab
لذلك أحد أكبر المساهمات المقدمة من مختبري
has been to combine rigid and soft materials
هي الجمع ما بين المواد الصلبة والمرنة
in very, very small mechanisms.
في آليات صغيرة للغاية.
So this jumping mechanism is about four millimeters on a side,
آلية القفز هذه هي عبارة عن حوالي أربعة مليمترات على الجانب،
so really tiny.
لذلك فهي صغيرة للغاية.
The hard material here is silicon, and the soft material is silicone rubber.
المادة الصلبة هنا هي السيليكون، والمادة اللينة هي مطاط السيليكون.
And the basic idea is that we're going to compress this,
والفكرة الأساسية هي أننا سنقوم بالضغط عليها،
store energy in the springs, and then release it to jump.
لنخزن الطاقة في الزنبركات، ومن ثم نفرج عنها للقفز.
So there's no motors on board this right now, no power.
حاليا لا توجد محركات ولا كهرباء على متن الروبوت.
This is actuated with a method that we call in my lab
يتم دفعها باستخدام طريقة نسميها في مختبري
"graduate student with tweezers." (Laughter)
"طالب دراسات عليا مع ملاقط."
So what you'll see in the next video
إذا ما سترونه في المقطع التالي
is this guy doing amazingly well for its jumps.
طالب يقوم بعمل مدهش لجعلها تقفز
So this is Aaron, the graduate student in question, with the tweezers,
هذا هو "آرون" طالب الدراسات العليا مع الملاقط
and what you see is this four-millimeter-sized mechanism
ترون آلية اﻷربع مليمترات
That's almost 100 times its own length.
ما يقارب 100 ضعف طولها.
And it survives, bounces on the table,
ومع ذلك ينجو، يرتد على الطاولة،
it's incredibly robust, and of course survives quite well until we lose it
إنه قوي بشكل لا يصدق، وينجو بشكل جيد حتى نضيعه
because it's very tiny.
لأنه صغير جدا.
Ultimately, though, we want to add motors to this too,
في النهاية، نريد أن نضيف محركات أيضا،
and we have students in the lab working on millimeter-sized motors
ولدينا طلاب في المختبر يعملون على محركات بحجم المليمتر
to eventually integrate onto small, autonomous robots.
لدمجها مع الروبوتات المستقلة الصغيرة الحجم.
But in order to look at mobility and locomotion at this size scale to start,
لكن من أجل تهيئة التنقل والحركة لمثل هذا الحجم من الروبوتات
we're cheating and using magnets.
نقوم بالاحتيال واستخدام المغناطيسات.
So this shows what would eventually be part of a micro-robot leg,
هذا يوضح ما سيكون جزء من ساق لروبوت دقيق الحجم،
and you can see the silicone rubber joints
ويمكنك أن ترى مفاصل السيليكون المطاطية
and there's an embedded magnet that's being moved around
وهناك مغناطيس مضمن يتم تحريكه
by an external magnetic field.
بواسطة حقل مغناطيسي خارجي.
So this leads to the robot that I showed you earlier.
يقودنا هذا إلى الروبوت الذي عرضته عليكم في وقت سابق.
The really interesting thing that this robot can help us figure out
والشيء المثير للاهتمام أن هذا الروبوت يمكن أن يساعدنا على اكتشاف
is how insects move at this scale.
كيفية حركة الحشرات الصغيرة الحجم.
We have a really good model for how everything
لدينا نموذج ممتاز يشرح بشكل شامل
from a cockroach up to an elephant moves.
آلية الحركة ابتداء من الصرصور إلى الفيل.
We all move in this kind of bouncy way when we run.
كلنا نتبع حركة الوثب عند الجري.
But when I'm really small, the forces between my feet and the ground
لكن إذا كنت صغيرة الحجم، القوى ما بين قدمي والأرض
are going to affect my locomotion a lot more than my mass,
ستأثر بحركتي أكثر بكثير من كتلتي.
which is what causes that bouncy motion.
وهو ما يسبب حركة الوثب.
So this guy doesn't work quite yet,
هذا الروبوت لا يعمل تماما حتى الآن،
but we do have slightly larger versions that do run around.
لكن لدينا نماذج أكبر قليلا تقوم بالتنقل والحركة.
So this is about a centimeter cubed, a centimeter on a side, so very tiny,
هذا حوالي سنتيمتر مكعب، سنتيمتر واحد على الجانب، لذلك هو صغير جدا،
and we've gotten this to run about 10 body lengths per second,
وقد استطعنا تهيئته ليجري ما يقارب 10 أضعاف طوله.
so 10 centimeters per second.
أي 10 سنتيمترات في الثانية.
It's pretty quick for a little, small guy,
هذا سريع جدا مقارنة بروبوت صغير الحجم.
and that's really only limited by our test setup.
وهو فقط محدود بسبب إعدادات الاختبار.
But this gives you some idea of how it works right now.
لكن يعطيك هذا الآن فكرة عن كيفية عمل الروبوت.
We can also make 3D-printed versions of this that can climb over obstacles,
نستطيع أيضا إنتاج نماذج ثلاثية اﻷبعاد، يمكنها الصعود فوق العقبات،
a lot like the cockroach that you saw earlier.
مثل الصرصور، الذي شاهدناه في وقت سابق.
But ultimately we want to add everything onboard the robot.
لكن في النهاية نريد إضافة كل شيء على متن الروبوت.
We want sensing, power, control, actuation all together,
نريد الاستشعار، والطاقة، والسيطرة، والنظام الميكانيكي كل ذلك معا،
and not everything needs to be bio-inspired.
ولا يجب استيحاء كل شيء من أسس بيولوجية.
So this robot's about the size of a Tic Tac.
هذا الروبوت بحجم سكاكر النعناع.
And in this case, instead of magnets or muscles to move this around,
الآن، بدلا من المغناطيس أو العضلات لإيحاد الحركة،
we use rockets.
نستخدم مواد.
So this is a micro-fabricated energetic material,
هذه مادة حيوية مختلقة دقيقة الحجم.
and we can create tiny pixels of this,
من هذه المادة نستطيع إنتاج بكسلات صغيرة الحجم.
and we can put one of these pixels on the belly of this robot,
ويمكننا وضع واحدة من هذه البكسلات على بطن هذا الروبوت،
and this robot, then, is going to jump when it senses an increase in light.
لذلك سيقوم الروبوت بالقفز عند استشعاره زيادة في الضوء.
So the next video is one of my favorites.
المقطع التالي هو أحد المقاطع المفضلة لدي.
So you have this 300-milligram robot
لديك روبوت بوزن 300 مليغرام
jumping about eight centimeters in the air.
يقفز ما يقارب 8 سنتيمترات في الهواء.
It's only four by four by seven millimeters in size.
حجمه (4) (4) (7) ملليمترات.
And you'll see a big flash at the beginning
في البداية سترى وميضا ساطعا
when the energetic is set off,
بعد تحرير الطاقة،
and the robot tumbling through the air.
ستجد الروبوت يتشقلب في الهواء.
So there was that big flash,
هذا هو الوميض،
and you can see the robot jumping up through the air.
وبعده ترى الروبوت يقفز عاليا في الهواء.
So there's no tethers on this, no wires connecting to this.
ليست هناك حبال ولا أسلاك متصلة بالروبوت.
Everything is onboard, and it jumped in response
كل شيء على متن الروبوت، وتم القفز على شكل ردة فعل
to the student just flicking on a desk lamp next to it.
للضوء الناتج عن مصباح المكتب الذي يقوم الطالب بإضاءته
So I think you can imagine all the cool things that we could do
لذلك أعتقد انه يمكنك أن تتخيل كل الأشياء الرائعة التي يمكن أن نقوم بها
with robots that can run and crawl and jump and roll at this size scale.
مع روبوتات صغيرة الحجم تستطيع الجري والزحف والقفز والتدحرج.
Imagine the rubble that you get after a natural disaster like an earthquake.
تخيل الركام الناتج بعد كارثة طبيعية مثل الزلزال.
Imagine these small robots running through that rubble
تخيل هذه الروبوتات الصغيرة تجول هذا الركام
to look for survivors.
للبحث عن ناجين.
Or imagine a lot of small robots running around a bridge
أو تخيل عددا كبيرا من الروبوتات تتجول حول جسر
in order to inspect it and make sure it's safe
من أجل فحصه والتأكد من أنه آمن
so you don't get collapses like this,
لكيلا تحصل على انهيارات مثل هذه
which happened outside of Minneapolis in 2007.
التي حدثت خارج مينيابوليس في عام 2007.
Or just imagine what you could do
أو فقط تخيل ما يمكن أن تفعله
if you had robots that could swim through your blood.
لو كان لديك روبوتات تسبح خلال الدم.
Right? "Fantastic Voyage," Isaac Asimov.
أليس كذلك؟ "رحلة رائعة" لإسحاق أسيموف.
Or they could operate without having to cut you open in the first place.
أو العمل دون الحاجة لشق الجسم في المقام الأول.
Or we could radically change the way we build things
أو نستطيع تغيير طرق صناعتنا للأشياء وبشكل جذري
if we have our tiny robots work the same way that termites do,
لو أمكننا جعل روبوتاتنا تعمل كالنمل اﻷبيض،
and they build these incredible eight-meter-high mounds,
وجعلناها تبني التلال العالية ذات الثمانية أمتار،
effectively well ventilated apartment buildings for other termites
وبناء مبان سكنية جيدة التهوية لغيرها من النمل اﻷبيض
in Africa and Australia.
في أفريقيا وأستراليا.
So I think I've given you some of the possibilities
لذلك أعتقد أنني أعطيتكم بعض احتمالات
of what we can do with these small robots.
ما يمكننا القيام به من خلال هذه الروبوتات الصغيرة.
And we've made some advances so far, but there's still a long way to go,
ونأمل أن نكون قد حققنا بعض التقدم إلى الآن لكن لا يزال أمامنا الكثير
and hopefully some of you can contribute to that destination.
ونأمل أن البعض منكم يمكنه المساهمة في تحقيق تلك الغاية.
Thanks very much.
شكرا جزيلا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)